Preliminary Inventory to the Jack G. Shaheen Collection on Arabs in U.S. Film and Television TAM.535
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Jack G. Shaheen Papers: Arabs in U.S. Film and Television
Bulk, 1970-2002
1940-2002
TAM.535
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
28.5 linear feet in 36 boxes
Born in 1935 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, Dr. Jack G. Shaheen, professor, author film and legal consultant, has studied and documented the history of damaging stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims in American media. Shaheen is currently (2011) a Distinguished Visiting Scholar at New York University’s Asian/Pacific/American Institute and The Hagop Kevorkian Center for Near Eastern Studies. This collection contains correspondence, research notes, published and unpublished writings, transcripts of his testimony in legal cases pertaining to discrimination against Arab Americans; research files (the bulk of the collection) that contain printed ephemera (sometimes annotated), including advertisements, clippings, reviews, editorial cartoons, as well as some motion picture posters and still photographs; two boxes of comic books containing Arab characters; two boxes of audiocassettes, consisting of interviews of Shaheen, some from the mass media, and recordings of radio programs.
Shaheen, Jack G, 1935-
Access Restrictions
This collection is currently being processed and is temporarily closed to researchers.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jack G. Shaheen Videos (Videos 015) contains nearly 3,000 motion pictures spanning from late-19th century silent films to contemporary Hollywood productions, and television programs including comedies, dramas, cartoons, as well as commercials, on VHS and DVDs, that depict Arabs and Arab Americans. For additional information about this collection, contact the repository at tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains correspondence, research notes, published and unpublished writings, transcripts of his testimony in legal cases pertaining to discrimination against Arab Americans; research files (the bulk of the collection) that contain printed ephemera (sometimes annotated), including advertisements, clippings, reviews, editorial cartoons, film scripts, including those for which he served as a consultant, as well as some motion picture posters and still photographs; two boxes of comic books containing Arab characters; two boxes of audiocassettes, consisting of interviews of Shaheen, some from the mass media, and recordings of radio programs.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dr. Jack G. Shaheen (1935- ), professor, author, film ( Syriana, Three Kings)and legal consultant, has studied and documented the history of damaging stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims in American media. He also has connected their development to the portrayals of other marginalized groups including Jews, Native Americans, Asian Americans, Latinos, and African Americans. Shaheen is currently (2011) a Distinguished Visiting Scholar at New York University’s Asian/Pacific/American Institute and The Hagop Kevorkian Center for Near Eastern Studies. Shaheen is the author of The TV Arab (1984), Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People (2001), and Guilty: Hollywood's Verdict on Arabs after 9/11 (2008).
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. The collection is grouped in to two series reflecting two separate accretions of the collection received from the donor in 2010 and 2012.
Sources
Media Education Foundation. “Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People.” Accessed September 30, 2010. http://www.mediaed.org/cgi-bin/commerce.cgi?preadd=action&key=412. REEL BAD ARABS: How Hollywood Vilifies a People, Featuring Dr. Jack Shaheen, “About Dr. Jack Shaheen,” Accessed September 30, 2010, http://www.reelbadarabs.com/drjack.html. Wolfman Productions, “Shattering Stereotypes: Dr. Jack G. Shaheen, Ph.D.,” Accessed September 30, 2010, http://www.wolfmanproductions.com/shaheen.html
Shaheen, Jack G, 1935-; Shaheen, Jack G, 1935-; Arabs in motion pictures |z United States.; Arabs in popular culture |z United States.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Comic books.; Interviews.; Manuscripts for publication.; Research notes.; Screenplays.; Stereotypes (Social psychology) in mass media |z United States.; Testimonies.
- 2010 Accession, 23.0 linear feet in 24 boxes
  - Records, 1980s-2000s (Box 1)
    General note
    Contains articles, essays, and speeches by Shaheen and research files relating to portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans in film and print.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 2)
    Contains some correspondence principally with universities, class notes, speeches, and articles by Shaheen, research files which include, in addition to articles and clippings, scripts and broadcast transcripts. Several files contain material comparing the portrayals of Arabs to those of Asians and African Americans.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 3)
    Contains Shaheen's correspondence with magazines and students, notes and clippings on fiction, films, and TV shows concerning portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans, a file titled Iraq War images (apparently for a journal article), video and DVD lists, a copy of the Arab World Notebook: Secondary School Level, and conference notes.
  - Records, 1980s-2000s (Box 4)
    Contains Shaheeen's film notes and clippings on portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans, lists of films with Arab stereotypes, a draft of Shaheen's book Reel Bad Arabs, and transcripts of his testimony and other legal documents on several discrimination harassment court cases for which he was a consultant.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
    Contain's Shaheen's testimony transcripts and other legal documents from discrimination harassment court cases that he was a consultant on as an expert witness, speeches and articles written by Shaheen about portrayals of Arabs in the media, his research notes concerning the portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans in film and print, and articles on Arab portrayals in the media not by Shaheen.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 6)
    Contains articles and speeches written by Shaheen concerning stereotypes and portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans in film and print and articles by others that he cited on portrayals of Arabs in the media.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 7)
    Contains film and TV reviews, notes from the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee conference (2000), research notes, speeches, and articles by Shaheen concerning portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans in film, TV, and print. Also contains articles on portrayal of Arabs in the media not by Shaheen.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 8)
    Contains articles by Shaheen concerning portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans in film and print and an editted draft of Reel Bad Arabs (2001) split into chapters "Introduction," "Sheik," "Villians," "Maidens," and "Palestinians." Also contains articles by others on the portrayal of Arabs in the media.
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 9)
    Contains correspondence, copies of comic strips, Shaheen's research notes on films concerning portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans, a list of films with Arab characters, draft of Reel Bad Arabs (2001), and a draft of the article the "Comic Book Arab" (1991). Also contains articles on portrayal of Arabs and other stereotypes in the media not by Shaheen.
  - Records, 1980s-2000s (Box 10)
    Contains copies of comic strips with Arab characters, posters related to Shaheen's book Reel Bad Arabs (2001), lists on Arab characters in comics, articles written by Shaheen about Arab portrayal in print and film, film consulting records for Three Kings (1999), including Shaheen's contract with Warner Brothers, and theses and dissertations submitted to Shaheen on Arabs. Also contains articles on portrayal of Arabs in the media not by Shaheen.
  - Records, 1967, 1970s-2000s (Box 11)
    Contains Shaheen's research notes and clippings concerning portrayals of Arabs in films (notes specify the chapter of Reel Bad Arabs and whether the film is a positive or negative portrayal of Arabs), a research proposal and essay for the Comic Book Arab, copies of editorial articles containing Arab stereotypes, and theses and dissertations submitted to Shaheen.
  - Records, 1990s (Box 12)
    Contains Shaheen's lists on types of stereotypes, research notes and clippings on film and movie serials concerning portrayals of Arabs (notes specify the chapter of Reel Bad Arabs, 2001, is noted in and whether the film is a positive or negative portrayal of Arabs), and copies of comics which contain Arab stereotyping.
  - Records, 1990s (Box 13)
    Contains Shaheen's film notes and clippings concerning portrayals of Arabs and Arab Americans (notes specify the chapter of Reel Bad Arabs, 2001, and whether the film is a positive or negative portrayal of Arabs).
  - Records, 1980s-2000s (Box 14)
    Contains Shaheen's articles concerning portrayals of Arabs, drafts of Reel Bad Arabs (2001) and a typescript for the TV Arab (1984). Also contains articles and film reviews on Arab portrayals in print and film not written by Shaheen.
  - Records, 1967, 1990s-2000s (Box 15)
    Contains a draft of Reel Bad Arabs (2001) and book reviews of Reel Bad Arabs and articles cited in Reel Bad Arabs, articles written by Shaheen including film and TV reviews, research notes and clippings on TV and film portrayals of Arabs, and a script by Shaheen called "Pinched Wire and Concrete."
  - Records, 1970s-2000s (Box 16)
    Contains correspondence, Arab-American Anti-Discrimination Committee conference notes and discrimination reports, research notes on film, commericials, and TV, editorial cartoons portraying Arabs, speeches written by Shaheen, and files on Alex Odeh, an Arab-American anti discrimination activist who was killed in a bombing in 1985. Also contains a draft of the TV Arab by Shaheen and television scripts.
  - Records, 1970s-1990s (Box 17)
    Contains correspondence with TV networks, research notes and clippings on portrayals of Arabs in TV movies, articles and cartoons on Arab stereotyping and Arabs in the media, reviews of Shaheen's book, Reel Bad Arabs (2001), a draft of the TV Arab (1984) by Shaheen, scripts with Arab characters from TV and film, theses submitted to Shaheen, and legal documents for court cases Shaheen consulted for as an expert witness.
  - Records, 1990s-2000s (Box 18)
    Contains student theses submitted to Shaheen on Arabs, consulting contracts, scripts of films and TV shows for which he was a consultant, including the films Syriana (2005) and Three Kings (1999), discrimination reports, articles on portrayals of Arabs in media, and a list of books and essays on stereotypes.
  - Records, undated (Box 19)
    Contains clippings and research notes on films concerning the portrayals of Arabs (notes specify the chapter of Reel Bad Arabs, 2001, and whether the film is a positive or negative portrayal of Arabs).
  - Records, undated (Box 20)
    Contains clippings and research notes on films concerning the portrayals of Arabs (notes specify the chapter of Reel Bad Arabs, 2001, and whether the film is a positive or negative portrayal of Arabs). Also contains comic books with Arab characters.
  - Records, 1943-1987 (Box 21)
    Contains comic books which were collected by Shaheen due to their portrayals of Arabs and also contains some notes on the portrayal of Arabs.
  - Records, 1987-2009, undated (Box 22)
  - Records, 1960s-1990s (Box 23)
    Contains audio cassettes of interviews with Shaheen, some from the mass media, and radio broadcasts that he recorded or purchased on the topic of Arabs in the media and protrayals of Arabs.
  - Records, 2000s, undated (Box 24)
- 2012 Accession, 5.5 linear feet in 12 boxes
  - Box 25
    Manuscript materials: Correspondence-Letters, Notes, E-Mails to and from Jack Shanheen; Research Notes; Research Notes and/or Presentation Notes; Records and Notes for the Jack G. and Bernice M. Shaheen Media Scholarship Fund; Jack Shaheen Speeches and Notes; Arab-American/Islamic-American Organizational Literature; Calendar and Business Papers; Iraq Attack Information; Misc. Papers)
  - Box 26
    Advertisements for films, Miscellaneous Graphics, and Movie Stills (Photographs) (Divided by archives assistant into the following folders, labeled: Anti-Islamic Photographs, Advertisement Photographs; Movie Stills; Television Stills; Cartoon Stills; Misc. Graphics; Cover/Magazine Art; Misc. (Satirical) Graphics; Printed Advertisements; Jack Shaheen Talk Flyer; Misc. Motion Picture Posters; The Lion Man Graphics; Netherlands and Switzerland Graphics)
  - Box 27
    Ephemera, Comic Strips, Editorial Comics (Divided by archives assistant into the following folders, labeled: Playboy; Editorial Comics-Misc. [three folders];Steve Roper and Mike Nomad Strips; Steve Canyon Strips; Brenda Starr Strips; Spiderman Strips; Prince Valiant Strips; Annie Strips; Comic Strips Misc.; Comics Misc.; Ephemera)
  - Box 28
    Periodicals (Divided by archives assistant into the following folders, labeled: Periodicals [there are two]; Newspaper Clippings and Articles; Newspaper Clippings and Articles for AK Comics: Middle East Heroes; William F. Buckley Jr.-Firing Line [there are two])
  - Box 29
    Comic Books and Photocopies of Comic Books
  - Box 30
    Mini-audio cassette tapes
  - Box 31
    Slides
  - Box 32
    Aartifacts
  - Box 33
    Artifacts
  - Box 34
    Books
  - Box 35
    Flat box containing two Aladdin placemats
  - Box 36
    Book, oversized: 50 Years of Movie Posters / John Kobal (1974) 6 folders containing movie posters 1 folder with poster of Shaheen Barnes & Noble Book Talk 1 folder with posters announcing Shaheen Presentation 1 folder with poster related to the portrayal of Arabs in Russian media 1 folder of newspaper clippings 1 folder of graphics and art 1 folder of advertisements
  - Oversize, undated (Flat-file 1, Drawer 10, Box MSOS003)
    Various posters for TV and movies.